<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academic notes</title>
    <description>Archive of academic notes</description>
    <link>/anotes/</link>
    <atom:link href="/anotes/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 18:02:48 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 18:02:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Royal Society's Multifunctional landscapes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;intro&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;intro&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;These are notes from my reading of the executive summary of the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://royalsociety.org/topics-policy/projects/living-landscapes/multifunctional-land-use/&quot;&gt;Multifunctional landscapes&lt;/a&gt; report the Royal Society published earlier this
week. The summary is really succinct and makes all the good points in five recommendations. These are some of my opinionated
highlights. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is a critical time for land use policy globally (e.g., climate change,
  energy crisis), but particularly in the UK (e.g., Brexit). Science and innovation have several important roles in helping manage landscapes better (the report lists several of them in detail).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 1&lt;/strong&gt; - embrace a multifunctional approach that considers multiple
market &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; non-market land-based outputs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 2&lt;/strong&gt; - the critical role of research and innovation, which needs
to be oriented to continue increasing the productivity and profitability of
farming, but also expanded in three critical ways: take a multifunctional perspective (see R.1);
pay much greater attention to sustainability; and carry out more research on landscape functions
and how they interact with each other (trade-off’s and synergies).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 3&lt;/strong&gt; - increase and adapt skills, training and advice for land managers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 4&lt;/strong&gt; - “A novel data science-driven approach is needed to develop
a high-quality common evidence base to underpin land use decisions”. This ons
hits really close to home, so I’m just going to reproduce it here verbatim:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;Decision-making&lt;/span&gt;  in multifunctional landscapes will benefit from integration of information about all aspects of landscapes including farm and forestry outputs, biophysical data (such as topography, climate, soils and biodiversity) and ecosystem services, as well as socioeconomic data such as land values, land ownership and livelihoods dependent on land-based-activities. Some of this information is available but is of variable quality, relevance, timeliness and accessibility. A more strategic national approach to land-based information, with clear data standards and protocols and creation of a common evidence platform, would empower decision-makers with a consistent set of science-based inputs from which to negotiate land use decisions. It would also facilitate the incorporation of new data streams made available by technological advances. Consistent and scientifically robust baselines, metrics and systematic monitoring programmes are needed to better understand the state of landscapes and what they are being used for, and to track progress towards meeting policy objectives.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendation 5&lt;/strong&gt; - We need &lt;em&gt;spatially explicit&lt;/em&gt; national land use frameworks
to judge the compatibility of different policy commitments. These need to be
based on robust data and analytics, and be transparent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt; The Royal Society (2023). &lt;em&gt;Multifunctional landscapes: Informing a long-term vision for managing the UK’s land - Executive summary&lt;/em&gt;. ISBN: 978-1-78252-633-9. &lt;a href=&quot;https://royalsociety.org/topics-policy/projects/living-landscapes/multifunctional-land-use/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;https://royalsociety.org/topics-policy/projects/living-landscapes/multifunctional-land-use/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/anotes/articles/23/rsml</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/anotes/articles/23/rsml</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open by Default talk</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This text was originally posted as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1547539954691182596&quot;&gt;Twitter
thread&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m super glad the lovely &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RSSMerseyside&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@RSSMerseyside&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hipyliv&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@hipyliv&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; folks put together the “Using open data sources” event and made the recording available:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/u3hYWLYApoA&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I contributed the talk “Open by default - Developing reproducible, computational research”. You can find more info about the talk at &lt;a href=&quot;https://urbangrammarai.xyz/blog/post29_obd.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In this post, I’ll provide a bit of background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;kitchen_sausage&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;kitchen_sausage&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FXnzBeyXwAAOWh0?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=4096x4096&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://urbangrammarai.xyz/talks/202206_rss_merseyside/index.html#/needs/0&quot;&gt;Slide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last +2 years, Martin Fleischmann and I have been working on the Urban Grammar project, funded by ESRC and the Alan Turing Institute to develop new ways of understanding (urban) form and function through (satellite) data and machine learning (all project info at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://urbangrammarai.xyz&quot;&gt;project page&lt;/a&gt;). From Day 1, we had very clear we wanted to take an open approach to the project, and that this shouldn’t only apply to its outputs, but also to the &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; to get there. From that point onward, almost every decision we made in the project was guided by that principle. The talk covers in a (roughly) structured the areas we paid particular attention, namely aspects of process (a.k.a. the “kitchen”) and aspects of output (a.k.a. the “sausage”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our taken on “Open by default” (by no means invented by us!) is based on three key principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FXn0yFfXEAQCHSI?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=4096x4096&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://urbangrammarai.xyz/talks/202206_rss_merseyside/index.html#/open-by-default-1&quot;&gt;Slide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;ORS&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;ORS&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;The quote, like so much inspiration, has been blatantly stolen from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00168-014-0611-7&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by Serge Rey (ironically, paywalled). &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re not claiming this will work for &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; research project, but it has for a data/computation intensive one like ours. We have discovered many things we didn’t anticipate (mostly how useful it is even just for us to constantly work in the open), and this talk is an attempt to put a bit of structure into those thoughts. The key takeaways though are simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FXn1ULnXoAEXK35?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=4096x4096&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://urbangrammarai.xyz/talks/202206_rss_merseyside/index.html#/the-takeaway&quot;&gt;Slide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In academia, we talk a lot about outputs, but very little about process. &lt;em&gt;How&lt;/em&gt; we do research and why different approaches yield different outcomes even if the results are seemingly the same matters. We should discuss it more, share best practices and learn from each other.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2022 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/anotes/articles/22/obd</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/anotes/articles/22/obd</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>WUF 11</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;wuf_img&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;wuf_img&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/anotes/assets/img/wuf.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;“Proof” I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; go to WUF 11&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I attended my first World Urban Forum (WUF), the UN’s biannual
jamboree to celebrate cities, work done on cities, and work to do on cities. I
confess that, for someone who’s be “doing cities” for the better part of 15
years, I’m a bit embarrassed it took me this long to show up to one of these.
I’m glad I did. So, while it’s still hot in my memory and before I go back to
the pile of email accummulated, I’ll try to commit to words a few of my
impressions. Expect some ideas on cities, some on conferences in the new
normal, and some on first-time conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with things I’ve learned about cities. I leave Katowice with a copy of
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://unhabitat.org/wcr/&quot;&gt;2022 World Cities Report&lt;/a&gt;, freshly released this week. More
importantly, I leave with the determination to spend some quality time with
the document, and giving some of the proposals in it the time they deserve.
Some of the ideas I picked up from the press release are intriguing (e.g.,
“localising” SDGs), others exciting (e.g., a new social contract channeled
through cities), and others I was more familiar with (e.g., 15-minute cities)
but it’s fantastic to see they have found their place in a document of this
caliber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I focused most my time on sessions that touch directly my areas of expertise.
Although not obvious at first sight, the WUF does bring together quite a few
data nerds to discuss the potential and risks of weaving technology and data
through the urban fabric. There were three highlights to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the session on the report on &lt;a href=&quot;https://wuf.unhabitat.org/event/ai-and-cities-guidelines-ethical-use-ai-local-authorities?user_id=4497598&amp;amp;first_name=Daniel&amp;amp;last_name=Arribas-Bel&amp;amp;email=d.arribas-bel@liverpool.ac.uk&amp;amp;lang=en-GB&amp;amp;session_id=615219&amp;amp;session_name=NE%2070%20%20-%20%20AI%20and%20Cities%20%3A%20guidelines%20for%20an%20ethical%20use%20of%20AI%20by%20local%20authorities&amp;amp;external_id=SCA-234280-4018834&quot;&gt;cities and AI&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;label for=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;The report itself has not been published yet, but I look forward to reading it when it does come
out &lt;/span&gt; It was great to see explicit brain power by a group of folks who
collectively really understand both cities and AI. Unfortunately, the
report itself has not been published yet, but I look forward to reading it
when it does come out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the session on &lt;a href=&quot;https://wuf.unhabitat.org/event/earth-observations-toolkit-sustainable-cities-and-human-settlements-supporting-evidence-based?user_id=4497598&amp;amp;first_name=Daniel&amp;amp;last_name=Arribas-Bel&amp;amp;email=d.arribas-bel@liverpool.ac.uk&amp;amp;lang=en-GB&amp;amp;session_id=615339&amp;amp;session_name=TE%2017%20-%20The%20Earth%20Observations%20Toolkit%20for%20Sustainable%20Cities%20and%20Human%20Settlements%20-%20Supporting%20Evidence-based%20policy-making%20for%20Equitable%20Urban%20Futures&amp;amp;external_id=SCA-234280-4018834&quot;&gt;earth observation for SDGs&lt;/a&gt;, which showcased a
bunch of really interesting projects in this space (pun intended!), including
UN’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://eotoolkit.unhabitat.org&quot;&gt;Earth Observation Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;, Prof. Yifang Ban’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://eo4sdg11.users.earthengine.app/view/sdg-1131-indicator&quot;&gt;Earth Enginge
app&lt;/a&gt; for SDG 11.3.1, or the South African’s space agency efforts to build
a “national GHSL”. My takeaway from this session however was brought by
Dennis Mwaniki from UN Habitat who noted that there is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of work on SDG
11.3.1 (“ratio
of land consumption rate to population growth rate”) and less in others (e.g.,
those on mobility and public transit), perhaps because it lends itself much
more to be addressed with tools which have developed greatly over the last
few years such as satellite technology. Food for thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third highlight has to do with GHSL. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghsl.jrc.ec.europa.eu/&quot;&gt;Global Human Settlement
Layer&lt;/a&gt; is the term used to refer to the family of data products on human
settlements on Earth that the European Commission (EC) and the Joint Research
Centre (JRC) has been pushing on at least since 2016. At this WUF, JRC
announced GHSL 2.0 which updates and widely expands the offering of datasets
made available. There was special love for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghsl.jrc.ec.europa.eu/degurba.php&quot;&gt;Degree of Urbanisation&lt;/a&gt;
product, which is now making its way into all sorts of policy arenas. To me
however the most significant anouncement was the news that, from next year
onwards, GHSL will transition from JRC into the Copernicus programme and will
thus become part of the family of data that ESA and EC regularly take care of
(think of it as a Sentinel mission for human settlements). As someone who’s
been watching the new forms of data lanscape for a few years now and has seen
many projects launch a flashy first release and then quickly wane, there is
something very refreshing about a team making efforts to not only innovate on
how we measure human activity but to ensure such advances have sustainability
over time. Bravo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides content, I learnt a lot about the “container”. WUF was my first big
conference (+16k people) since COVID. It was live streamed for free for anyone
to join remotely. In some ways, the space helped blend the hybrid experience:
many sessions were on a (really) large hangar-like space that had been
subdivided with very thin walls and no ceilings. Rather than piping sound into
speakers for every room (which would make the whole thing quite the
cacophony), sound was shared directly on the web stream and on headphones that
everyone picked up at the begining of the session and left at the end for
charging. Maybe this is standard in UN-land, but it was new to me, and I
really liked it. It made the streaming, and live translation when available
(main sessions) much more a first-class citizen experience because everyone
was essentially augmenting their experience with headphones. It made it
possible to have a lot of parallel sessions in essentially the same big space.
And it also made bringing remote speakers (e.g., many folks saw their flights
cancelled last minute) to a panel or a talk much more natural for similar
reasons as above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a few thoughts on my own experience as a WUF newbie. The first is that
the “UN vibes” that emmanate from all over the conference are just very cool.
As an academic, I’m used to one very particular type of conference, and
experiencing what a truly global community of policy makers, practitioners,
and other academics excited about cities feels like was super nice.
At times, I felt like I was in
the middle of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://us.macmillan.com/series/thecentenalcycle&quot;&gt;Malka Older novel&lt;/a&gt; or in one of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Expanse_(TV_series)&quot;&gt;The Expanse&lt;/a&gt;
episodes around the futuristic UN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, this was a conference a bit out of my comfort zone and
definitely beyond my usual networks. As a full professor who’s been regularly going to
conferences for over a decade, it was at once refreshing, overwhelming, and
humbling to be in one where you almost don’t know anyone.
In some ways, coming to WUF made me (more) aware of the challenges for early
career folk who attend their first conferences, and I hope I can take some of
this feeling into action in events I’m more involved.
Finally, it was also a good
reminder that the temptation is big to think that, as we become more senior,
we enjoy conferences more because we learn to “do conferences” better; but in
fact, it is more likely that we find “our crowd” and limit ourselves to it for
the most part. Stepping out of this pattern is challenging but important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, WUF 11 has been been a blast. I’ve learned a lot, met some very
cool people, and left with a renewed sense of awe and urgency about working on
cities. I’m glad I came and I hope it is not the last time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/anotes/articles/22/wuf</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/anotes/articles/22/wuf</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Professor</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This text was originally posted as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1503648739868790787&quot;&gt;Twitter
thread&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month I was promoted to Professor at Liverpool. To say I’m
humbled is a bit of an understatement… It’s still a blur and suspect
it’ll take a while to sink in. So, while that percolates, here’s
a thought crystal clear in my mind: they call it “chair”, but professor
really should be “bench”.
If the “chair” is partly reward for the achievements of a career, it
really would be best represented as a bench that can accommodate all
the folks who’ve make it possible. And there’re always many of them!
Part of it is the proverbial “giant shoulder-standing”, but there is
also the more down-to-earth mentorship, collaboration, peer-support,
and general “ass saving” academic networks provide when everything
else falls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I cannot think of a single achievement I’m truly proud of
for which I’m solely responsible. It is impossible to understand my
career without the context in which it’s happened, and that has always
been one or another community or colective. So, while I truly am
chuffed about the sound of “prof Dani”, let’s not forget
how these successes are really made and the mechanisms and social
infrastructure that makes them possible. And let’s nurture them
accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/anotes/articles/22/prof</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/anotes/articles/22/prof</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Levelling Up &amp; Moran's I</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This text was originally posted as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1489162746046394369&quot;&gt;Twitter
thread&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plenty of folks better placed to deliver hot takes so I’ll spare you mine… But, by my own account, the most statistically sophisticated fig in the full &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#levellingupwhitepaper&lt;/code&gt; is one on spatial stats(!). Gist: not wrong, not right either, but definitely cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqCju7XoBojrke?format=png&amp;amp;name=medium&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The Figure&amp;#8230;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot shows Moran’s I vs deprivation prevalence in Local Authorities. What’s Moran’s I? I’m glad you asked, this is a staple of Geographic &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#DataScience&lt;/code&gt; and spatial analysis courses alike (like mine! &lt;a href=&quot;https://darribas.org/gds_course/&quot;&gt;https://darribas.org/gds_course/&lt;/a&gt;. Moran’s I measures global spatial autocorrelation, capturing the degree to which values concentrate spatially. For a bit more on spatial autocorrelation, here’s me in my living room last year explaining pandemic-distanced students what it is in &amp;lt;10min:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqG2QmX0AAz5Bk?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=medium&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;Me, my living room, and spatial autocorrelation (check out the video &lt;a href=&quot;https://darribas.org/gds_course/content/bF/concepts_F.html#spatial-autocorrelation&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moran’s I is also a way to “summarise a map” in that it assigns a value to a pattern of spatial concentration. Your map looks like this? Moran’s I is high and approaching 1…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqHa_xXEAIBxJe?format=png&amp;amp;name=900x900&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;High Moran&amp;#8217;s I&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your map looks like this? Moran’s I will be low and approaching -1…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqHjSQWUAUeFg9?format=png&amp;amp;name=900x900&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;Low Moran&amp;#8217;s I&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, these figures are created using a small simulation tool&lt;label for=&quot;voila&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;voila&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Launch it on the cloud from
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mybinder.org/repo/darribas/int_sp_auto&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqH7yJXEAEyjPG?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=medium&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Thanks to the
voila team &amp;amp; &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@mybinderteam&lt;/code&gt; for the awesome infrastructure powering
this! &lt;/span&gt; I
wrote to help students grasp the intuition behind the statistic, and
you too can play with it! For a 14 minute version of what is Moran’s I and why you should love it, welcome back to my living room!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqI3LWXEAIEYD3?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=medium&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;Me, my living room, and Moran&amp;#8217;sI (check out the video &lt;a href=&quot;https://darribas.org/gds_course/content/bF/concepts_F.html#global-spatial-autocorrelation&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me back to Figure 1.23 in yesterday’s white paper, which took me a bit to decipher because it uses Moran’s I in a non-standard way. The point it’s trying to make is that cities w/ more income deprived population tend to display deprivation more spatially concentrated. This is an interesting pattern because it is saying that cities with more deprivation are also different in the way the deprivation is structured spatially (ie. more deprivation is related to more fundamental changes in how this is spatially configured).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while the graph is not wrong… it is also not entirely correct. It is well understood that Moran’s I scores (the statistic itself, which is on the vertical axis of the figure) are not directly comparable across different geographies. The reason is a bit technical, but has to do with comparing different sample sizes and spatial configurations of values. A topic for another thread perhaps… More importantly, Moran’s I is not that useful as a deterministic statistic, as a score. A value of 0.3 can mean something very different in two different local authorities. This has to do again with the underlying assumptions of the statistic, but mostly because in some cases we will have enough evidence to say that value points to spatial concentration and, in others, it will be indistinguishable from a completely spatially random map. I’d have probably used any visual cue (eg. dimming non-significant values) to emphasize this aspect and bring more nuance to the figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, let me repeat the figure is not wrong. Using raw Moran’s I scores to gauge broad patterns is a sensible strategy to &lt;em&gt;explore&lt;/em&gt; your data. Whether I’d choose to include the figure as it is on a final report is a different question…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to wrap up, although there are always ways to improve, I think it is awesome that policy makers are using these tools to inform their views on the world the decide on. This will be a very good example for prospective geography students on why they should take my numbers course even though what they really want is to “make a difference in politics”! Could it be improved the way these statistics are used in policy? Of course, but that is as much a job of policy makers as it is for us academics and data scientists “in the know”. The solution is not to remove the figure, but to have more of them, and to generate discussion around it so, over time, we all collectively get better at using data and stats for big policy “things”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s a wrap! If the nerdy bits of this post peeked your interest, consider spending a bit more time on the course website&lt;label for=&quot;Website&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Website&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://darribas.org/gds_course&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;https://darribas.org/gds_course&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt; or on the YouTube playlist&lt;label for=&quot;Playlist&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Playlist&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLaYT7Y2aK2d6vs3h38jnjrTEpSS7VYLwU&quot;&gt;YouTube Playlist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;! See you on the next big policy paper that uses spatial stats!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/anotes/articles/22/lu</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/anotes/articles/22/lu</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Best books of 2021</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This text was originally posted as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1475505545146683397&quot;&gt;Twitter
thread&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a “best-of-the-year-list spirit” on, and similar to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1340979325269667842&quot;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;, these past twelve months I have been able to maintain a bit more sanity and fill in the travelling gap with books. Here’s my Top-3 (with a bonus for good measure), in no particular order as they’re all equally different and amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FHn6U_7XIAgp5Cn?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=large&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The year in books&amp;#8230;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Ministry for the Future”, by Kim Stanley Robinson, is a space to think about life on earth in the next century more than anything else. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1380477463449468929&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; is what I said about it in April and, also related, &lt;a href=&quot;https://darribas.org/anotes/articles/21/ipcc&quot;&gt;here’re my thoughts&lt;/a&gt; from august about the IPCC recent report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blockchain Chicken Farm, by Xiaowei Wang, is a fascinating collection of short stories about how technology and the XXIst Century intersect with rural China. Insightful, respectful, and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite urban(-related) read of the year was Sarah Williams’s Data Action. Again, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1369573142423863301&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is what I said back in March, and it’s still fresh as freshly ground coffee beans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Honorary mention (because I’m &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; reading, but already &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; it’s part of the List) goes to the 2nd Ed of Francois Chollet’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.manning.com/books/deep-learning-with-python&quot;&gt;Deep Learning with Python&lt;/a&gt;. Intuitive, big-picture, and &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; practical. I wish every bit of data science had a book like this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re still reading and want to lurk more, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1340979325269667842&quot;&gt;here’s my list from 2020&lt;/a&gt;.
I’m always on the hunt for good books on computers, cities, and data (or anything else worth reading!) so, if you have good recommendations, feel free to send them my way!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/anotes/articles/21/bestofbooks</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/anotes/articles/21/bestofbooks</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open Data Products paper</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This text was originally posted as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1451522005505875992&quot;&gt;Twitter
thread&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with Mark Green, Francisco Rowe, and Alex Singleton, we have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10109-021-00363-5&quot;&gt;new paper&lt;/a&gt; out in the Journal of Geographical Systems pushing forward the idea of Open Data Products as a vehicle to make (Geographic) Data Science more impactful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We define Open Data Product as &lt;em&gt;“the open result of transparent processes
through which a variety of data (open and not) are turned into accessible
information through a service, infrastructure, analytics or a combination of
all of them, where each step of development follows open principles.&lt;/em&gt; We argue there’re at least three building blocks of an ODP: a need, a value proposition, Geographic Data Science, and outreach. Let me unpack each a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the need. ODPs are born out of trying to scratch an itch. We think this process is most useful when co-produced with stake-holders who’ll benefit from it most. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/markalangreen/status/1448266593654480899&quot;&gt;recent award&lt;/a&gt; to our own Mark Green and Jacob MacDonald for Local Data Spaces is a great example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, value: it’s not enough to identify a gap, ODPs also need to &lt;em&gt;fill&lt;/em&gt; it beyond what is available. This means publishing existing datasets on their own is usually not enough. So, how do you add value?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, Geographic Data Science. Geographic Data Science: we argue, given the undergoing data revolution where many datasets are not quite ready for use at the point of release, much of the contribution of ODPs resides in applying &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/gean.12194&quot;&gt;(Geographic) Data Science&lt;/a&gt; to turn them into analysis-ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth, outreach. Just because something is “out there” doesn’t mean people know about it or will use it. Paraphrasing the old say: “if you build it, they’ll come… if you call them, signpost the way, and welcome them”. Another home-grown example of good outreach includes the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Fcorowe/status/1419929045861605380&quot;&gt;work&lt;/a&gt; led by our own Francisco Rowe and Nikos Patias to inform policies on inequalities in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the paper we also identify challenges that will probably make the world see less ODPs than it should, mostly related to incentives &amp;amp; sustainability. We need to be mindful and work around them… And, finally, we close drawing parallels w/ the open source software revolution from 20 years ago. The “new kid in the block” is not software anymore but data, and most research will be unlocked (or not) by what we do with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A last note: we started this four years ago and a lot has happened in the world of data. If anything, my personal view is we underestimated the effects of some of the developments we documented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, it is now out for everyone to read and, hopefully, comment/rant/(dis)agree and stimulate the conversation so we can make the most out of what we believe is the most significant changes for the (social) sciences this century.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/anotes/articles/21/odp</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/anotes/articles/21/odp</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>IPCC AR6 report</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This text was originally posted as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1428636769822597121&quot;&gt;Twitter
thread&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know the IPCC’s first instalment of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/&quot;&gt;AR6 report&lt;/a&gt; came out  last week, but it’s taken me a few days to digest. A few thoughts, more as a journaling exercise than anything else. In short: we need geography, data (science), and cities more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it’s stating the obvious but, as they say, the report makes for a “sober read”. I can’t understand anyone reading this and not concluding climate change is one of if not the defining event of our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, Geography. Much of the discussion is rightly around the global figures. I get this because you have to start communicating somewhere and this is probably a good start. But what the report makes clear to me is how uneven the physics of climate change are across space. To me this means understanding the nuance of geographical variation, boosting spatial thinking, and using it to integrate views is going to be in hot (pun intended) demand. If only we had a discipline that deals with much of this already… oh wait!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, data (science). This is again stating the obvious, but understanding and coping with climate change requires (a lot) of data and ways of making sense of them. This is not a “Data Science is the holy grail and will save us”  pitch, but ignoring that we need this tech and the skills required as part of the answer is even more deluded. We need more people comfortable working with modern data across the board (science, industry &amp;amp; gov).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth, cities. I found one ref in the summary report, and it’s not pretty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E9OEAurX0AUdlP5?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=large&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Page 25. Summary for Policy Makers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report is focused on the physical fundamentals, and I’d expect to see more (and cheerier) on cities in the subsequent ones focused on impacts and adaptation. My view on cities and climate change is that they may generate localised effects but, paraphrasing the saying, “try the alternative”. That is, lodging the same amount of people and interactions in any other “form factor”. At any rate, cities are not all of the same kind, and we need more brain power directed at identifying how and making cities more climate change “aware”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all for now. My very strong recommendation is you pick up the “Summary for Policymakers”&lt;label for=&quot;report-url&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;report-url&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt; and give it a go. It’s not a “page turner” and it’s definitely not the Schitt’s Creek of reports. But it’s worth every second of your time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/anotes/articles/21/ipcc</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/anotes/articles/21/ipcc</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
