<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academic notes</title>
    <description>Archive of academic notes</description>
    <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/anotes/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/anotes/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 08:35:58 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 08:35:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Professor</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This text was originally posted as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1503648739868790787&quot;&gt;Twitter
thread&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month I was promoted to Professor at Liverpool. To say I’m
humbled is a bit of an understatement… It’s still a blur and suspect
it’ll take a while to sink in. So, while that percolates, here’s
a thought crystal clear in my mind: they call it “chair”, but professor
really should be “bench”.
If the “chair” is partly reward for the achievements of a career, it
really would be best represented as a bench that can accommodate all
the folks who’ve make it possible. And there’re always many of them!
Part of it is the proverbial “giant shoulder-standing”, but there is
also the more down-to-earth mentorship, collaboration, peer-support,
and general “ass saving” academic networks provide when everything
else falls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I cannot think of a single achievement I’m truly proud of
for which I’m solely responsible. It is impossible to understand my
career without the context in which it’s happened, and that has always
been one or another community or colective. So, while I truly am
chuffed about the sound of “prof Dani”, let’s not forget
how these successes are really made and the mechanisms and social
infrastructure that makes them possible. And let’s nurture them
accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/anotes/articles/22/prof</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/anotes/articles/22/prof</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Levelling Up &amp; Moran's I</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This text was originally posted as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1489162746046394369&quot;&gt;Twitter
thread&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plenty of folks better placed to deliver hot takes so I’ll spare you mine… But, by my own account, the most statistically sophisticated fig in the full &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#levellingupwhitepaper&lt;/code&gt; is one on spatial stats(!). Gist: not wrong, not right either, but definitely cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqCju7XoBojrke?format=png&amp;amp;name=medium&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The Figure&amp;#8230;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot shows Moran’s I vs deprivation prevalence in Local Authorities. What’s Moran’s I? I’m glad you asked, this is a staple of Geographic &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#DataScience&lt;/code&gt; and spatial analysis courses alike (like mine! &lt;a href=&quot;https://darribas.org/gds_course/&quot;&gt;https://darribas.org/gds_course/&lt;/a&gt;. Moran’s I measures global spatial autocorrelation, capturing the degree to which values concentrate spatially. For a bit more on spatial autocorrelation, here’s me in my living room last year explaining pandemic-distanced students what it is in &amp;lt;10min:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqG2QmX0AAz5Bk?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=medium&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;Me, my living room, and spatial autocorrelation (check out the video &lt;a href=&quot;https://darribas.org/gds_course/content/bF/concepts_F.html#spatial-autocorrelation&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moran’s I is also a way to “summarise a map” in that it assigns a value to a pattern of spatial concentration. Your map looks like this? Moran’s I is high and approaching 1…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqHa_xXEAIBxJe?format=png&amp;amp;name=900x900&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;High Moran&amp;#8217;s I&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your map looks like this? Moran’s I will be low and approaching -1…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqHjSQWUAUeFg9?format=png&amp;amp;name=900x900&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;Low Moran&amp;#8217;s I&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, these figures are created using a small simulation tool&lt;label for=&quot;voila&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;voila&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Launch it on the cloud from
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mybinder.org/repo/darribas/int_sp_auto&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqH7yJXEAEyjPG?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=medium&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Thanks to the
voila team &amp;amp; &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@mybinderteam&lt;/code&gt; for the awesome infrastructure powering
this! &lt;/span&gt; I
wrote to help students grasp the intuition behind the statistic, and
you too can play with it! For a 14 minute version of what is Moran’s I and why you should love it, welcome back to my living room!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FKqI3LWXEAIEYD3?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=medium&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;Me, my living room, and Moran&amp;#8217;sI (check out the video &lt;a href=&quot;https://darribas.org/gds_course/content/bF/concepts_F.html#global-spatial-autocorrelation&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me back to Figure 1.23 in yesterday’s white paper, which took me a bit to decipher because it uses Moran’s I in a non-standard way. The point it’s trying to make is that cities w/ more income deprived population tend to display deprivation more spatially concentrated. This is an interesting pattern because it is saying that cities with more deprivation are also different in the way the deprivation is structured spatially (ie. more deprivation is related to more fundamental changes in how this is spatially configured).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while the graph is not wrong… it is also not entirely correct. It is well understood that Moran’s I scores (the statistic itself, which is on the vertical axis of the figure) are not directly comparable across different geographies. The reason is a bit technical, but has to do with comparing different sample sizes and spatial configurations of values. A topic for another thread perhaps… More importantly, Moran’s I is not that useful as a deterministic statistic, as a score. A value of 0.3 can mean something very different in two different local authorities. This has to do again with the underlying assumptions of the statistic, but mostly because in some cases we will have enough evidence to say that value points to spatial concentration and, in others, it will be indistinguishable from a completely spatially random map. I’d have probably used any visual cue (eg. dimming non-significant values) to emphasize this aspect and bring more nuance to the figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, let me repeat the figure is not wrong. Using raw Moran’s I scores to gauge broad patterns is a sensible strategy to &lt;em&gt;explore&lt;/em&gt; your data. Whether I’d choose to include the figure as it is on a final report is a different question…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to wrap up, although there are always ways to improve, I think it is awesome that policy makers are using these tools to inform their views on the world the decide on. This will be a very good example for prospective geography students on why they should take my numbers course even though what they really want is to “make a difference in politics”! Could it be improved the way these statistics are used in policy? Of course, but that is as much a job of policy makers as it is for us academics and data scientists “in the know”. The solution is not to remove the figure, but to have more of them, and to generate discussion around it so, over time, we all collectively get better at using data and stats for big policy “things”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s a wrap! If the nerdy bits of this post peeked your interest, consider spending a bit more time on the course website&lt;label for=&quot;Website&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Website&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://darribas.org/gds_course&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;https://darribas.org/gds_course&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt; or on the YouTube playlist&lt;label for=&quot;Playlist&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Playlist&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLaYT7Y2aK2d6vs3h38jnjrTEpSS7VYLwU&quot;&gt;YouTube Playlist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;! See you on the next big policy paper that uses spatial stats!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/anotes/articles/22/lu</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/anotes/articles/22/lu</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>IPCC AR6 report</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This text was originally posted as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1428636769822597121&quot;&gt;Twitter
thread&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know the IPCC’s first instalment of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/&quot;&gt;AR6 report&lt;/a&gt; came out  last week, but it’s taken me a few days to digest. A few thoughts, more as a journaling exercise than anything else. In short: we need geography, data (science), and cities more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it’s stating the obvious but, as they say, the report makes for a “sober read”. I can’t understand anyone reading this and not concluding climate change is one of if not the defining event of our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, Geography. Much of the discussion is rightly around the global figures. I get this because you have to start communicating somewhere and this is probably a good start. But what the report makes clear to me is how uneven the physics of climate change are across space. To me this means understanding the nuance of geographical variation, boosting spatial thinking, and using it to integrate views is going to be in hot (pun intended) demand. If only we had a discipline that deals with much of this already… oh wait!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, data (science). This is again stating the obvious, but understanding and coping with climate change requires (a lot) of data and ways of making sense of them. This is not a “Data Science is the holy grail and will save us”  pitch, but ignoring that we need this tech and the skills required as part of the answer is even more deluded. We need more people comfortable working with modern data across the board (science, industry &amp;amp; gov).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth, cities. I found one ref in the summary report, and it’s not pretty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E9OEAurX0AUdlP5?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=large&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Page 25. Summary for Policy Makers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report is focused on the physical fundamentals, and I’d expect to see more (and cheerier) on cities in the subsequent ones focused on impacts and adaptation. My view on cities and climate change is that they may generate localised effects but, paraphrasing the saying, “try the alternative”. That is, lodging the same amount of people and interactions in any other “form factor”. At any rate, cities are not all of the same kind, and we need more brain power directed at identifying how and making cities more climate change “aware”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all for now. My very strong recommendation is you pick up the “Summary for Policymakers”&lt;label for=&quot;report-url&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;report-url&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt; and give it a go. It’s not a “page turner” and it’s definitely not the Schitt’s Creek of reports. But it’s worth every second of your time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/anotes/articles/21/ipcc</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/anotes/articles/21/ipcc</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
